<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: clojure | The Limiting Factor]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/categories/clojure/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T11:58:12+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Martin Clausen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Om my CSP]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2014/06/15/Om-my-CSP/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-15T19:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2014/06/15/Om-my-CSP</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looks like I will be at <a href="http://gotocon.com/cph-2014/">goto CPH</a> again this year.</p>

<p>The format this year is quite different, but looks very interesting nonetheless. Especially the Leading &amp; Bleeding Edge trakc looks interesting. At this track I am especially looking forward to seeing <a href="http://gotocon.com/cph-2014/speaker/David+Nolen">David Nolen&rsquo;s</a> talk <a href="http://gotocon.com/cph-2014/presentation/Immutability:%20Putting%20The%20Dream%20Machine%20To%20Work">Putting the Dream Machine to Work</a>.</p>

<p>David has created a <a href="https://github.com/clojure/clojurescript">ClojureScript</a> framework on top of <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/">React</a> called <a href="https://github.com/swannodette/om">Om</a>. Om is not just a wrapper around React. It leverages ClojureScript&rsquo;s immutable datastructures to substitute costly object and array compares with reference equality checks. This results in quite significant <a href="http://swannodette.github.io/2013/12/17/the-future-of-javascript-mvcs/">performance improvements</a>.</p>

<p>David in his <a href="https://github.com/swannodette/om/wiki/Basic-Tutorial#intercomponent-communication">tutorials</a> encourage another ClojureScript feature <a href="https://github.com/clojure/core.async">core.async</a> for intercomponent communication.</p>

<p>As Om is still very new there are not many presentations available but <a href="https://vimeo.com/97516219">Functional UI programming with React.JS and ClojureScript</a> is a very good introduction.</p>

<p>If you understand Norwegian (and maybe even if you don&rsquo;t) <a href="https://github.com/magnars">Magnar Sveen</a> and <a href="https://github.com/cjohansen">Christian Johansen</a> have recorded a very entertaining series of pair programming screencast where they use ClojureScript, <a href="https://github.com/levand/quiescent">Quiescent</a> (an alternative React ClojureScript library) and a TDD approach to create a Zombie themed Memory Flash Game called <a href="http://www.zombieclj.no/">ZOMBIECLJ</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Simple Chat App Using Aleph, Websockets and Clojure]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/08/27/a-simple-chat-app-using-clojure-aleph-and-websockets/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-27T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/08/27/a-simple-chat-app-using-clojure-aleph-and-websockets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have implemented a small example shoving how to use the websocket support in <a href="http://github.com/ztellman/aleph">Aleph</a>, asynchronous webframework for <a href="http://clojure.org/">Clojure</a> built on <a href="http://www.jboss.org/netty">Netty</a>.</p>

<p>The example is tested with Chrome and Firefox on Ubuntu. It should work in all modern browsers as it relies on <a href="http://github.com/gimite/web-socket-js/">web-socket-js</a> for websocket emulation in browsers that do not have native support. Please note the updated Usage instructions. The socket-policy-server necessary for Flash websocket emulation has to listen on port 843 (at least that is the first place Flash asks for the policy file) so the server has to be run using sudo.</p>

<p>If you are interested the example is at hosted on <a href="http://github.com/maacl/aleph-ws-test">github</a>, along with usage instructions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojure, Jetty 7 and WebSockets]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/07/28/clojure-jetty-7-and-websockets/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-28T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/07/28/clojure-jetty-7-and-websockets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found this <a href="http://gist.github.com/281490">gist</a> by Chris McDevitt&nbsp;which is a simple chat server and browser client that uses Jetty 7, Clojure and WebSockets.</p>

<p>I turned out to be quite a hassle to get it running so I thought I would document it here so others might save some time.</p>

<p>I have create a <a href="http://github.com/maacl/websocket-test">project</a> on github that includes all the dependencies. I run it in Emacs using swank-clojure-project. The two last forms start the two servers – one is the websocket chat server, the other just serves the index.html file (this is necessary for the web_socket.js&nbsp; to work). I have only been able to make this work in browsers with native websocket support (Chrome and Safari). If anybody can figure out what goes wrong in the other browsers (e.g. Firefox) let me know, and I will update.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
