<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: law | The Limiting Factor]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/categories/law/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-30T16:46:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Martin Clausen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flexible Contracts]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2013/09/14/flexible-contracts/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2013/09/14/flexible-contracts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="/posts/20130914000000.markdown"></h4>


<p>It was suggested to me to look into the concept of <a href="http://flexiblecontracts.com/">Flexible Contracts</a>, a new approach to contracting for agile it projects championed by Gabrielle Benefield who will be providing training in agile practices in connection with <a href="http://gotocon.com/aarhus-2013/">goto Aarhus 2013</a>.</p>

<p>Flexible Contracts are born out of the observation that traditional contract models are a very poor fit for agile IT projects. This is hardly a novel observation, but Gabrielle&rsquo;s work (and that of her collaborators) distinguishes itself by actually having produced a practical alternative, which they have commendably licensed under the <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">CC Attribution 3.0 Unported license</a>. Only the lite version &ndash; Flexlite 0.1 as it is designated &ndash; appears to be presently available, and can be accessed if you are willing to sign up to the Flexible Contracts mailing list <a href="http://flexiblecontracts.com/list/">here</a>.</p>

<p>It is worth noting that the overview attached to the contract clearly states that the Flexlite contract is to be considered a &ldquo;minimum viable contract&rdquo;, but after having reviewed the document I still find that the current version lacking in a number of ways.</p>

<p>Below I will outline a subset of the issues I have identified and for some suggests some possible remedies. Please note that I am commenting on the UK version (which you might want to keep handy if you want to make sense of my comments) of the contract which is the system of law I am most familiar with, but most of my comments should apply to both versions, with the exception of the issue of &ldquo;best endeavours&rdquo; where there is a significant difference between US and UK law.</p>

<h2>Statetment of Target Outcomes (SOTO)</h2>

<p>The contract focuses on the use of SOTOs instead of specifying the desired results through requirements or a more traditional solution specification. A SOTO:</p>

<blockquote><p>means a statement of target outcomes as agreed by the parties in accordance with clause 1.1;</p></blockquote>

<p>According to clause 2.2 the Supplier must for each Target Outcome create:</p>

<blockquote><p>Options that have the potential to achieve the Target Outcome.  In respect of each Option the Supplier shall provide a forecast in terms of the estimated value, costs, risks and expiry date (if any) for that Option and shall inform the Customer of any requirements for execution of the Option and any circumstances in which the Option may expire.</p></blockquote>

<p>Even after reading the overview it remains unclear exactly what the function of the Options are and what, if any, the work-flow for calling these are.</p>

<p>It appears odd that acceptance (adoption) of the Outcome Delivery is left to the Supplier but I assume this is considered reasonable given that one of the objectives of the Flexible Contract is to provide as much flexibility to vendor in deciding in how to achieve the SOTO. I don&rsquo;t think any customer would be comfortable with this construct, especially if the Supplier&rsquo;s payment hinges in part on achieving the Target Outcomes, which is one of the models (option B) suggested in the model SOTO schedule attached to the contract. Clause 2.7 isn&rsquo;t much help in this context, as 2.7. (a) is stating the obvious and (b) lacks fundamental precision. As such in can easily be interpreted as granting the Customer defacto veto rights against any Outcome Delivery, which is hardly constructive either.</p>

<p>Related to this issue is the lack of consistency between clause 3.1 which states that:</p>

<blockquote><p>In consideration of the provision of the Services by the Supplier, the Customer shall pay the fees in the amount and on the dates or with the frequency as set out in each SOTO.</p></blockquote>

<p>and the &ldquo;Hybrid Outcome-based fees&rdquo; model in the model SOTO schedule, where payment is conditioned upon achieving the Target Outcomes.</p>

<h2>Best Endeavours</h2>

<p>I also find it fundamentally concerning that the contract relies on a unqualified &ldquo;best endeavours&rdquo; standard when defining the Suppliers responsibility under the contract. It is simply not good practice not to agree some further specification of what the parties intend &ldquo;best endeavours&rdquo; to mean. This can for instance be done by indicating what financial/resources the Supplier must expend in its attempt to fulfill its obligation. Failing to provide such guidance is to invite conflict and to introduce unnecessary uncertainty. While I applaud the authors stated aim of brevity this is not an area where one wants to sacrifice lack of precision for terseness. I have included a few links below that provides more in-depth information on the subject.</p>

<h2>Intellectual Property Rights (IPR)</h2>

<p>The IPR as specified in clause 5 model appears fairly sensible and reflects the reality of the deliverables being a composite of bespoke, vendor, third party proprietary and FOSS. That said the specific license granted to the Customer in respect of Supplier Software (clause 5.4) will in many cases have to be adapted to the needs of the Customers, both in respect of scope but also rights to create derived works etc. I would suggest moving the specification of this license to the SOTO schedule to facilitate this. This also applies to the specification of what types of software (Customised, Supplier, Third Party, Open Source) will constitute part of the Outcome Delivery, so the Customer may determine the feasibility of the rights obtained and clear any necessary rights.</p>

<p>While the contract does provide a warranty for non-infringement in respect of the Services and Outcome Delivery it does not address the issue of indemnification for such infringement, which any prudent customer will require.</p>

<p>The above is a summary of some of the issues I have identified with the current draft of the Flexlite contract. I summation I think the contract does a good job of capturing the idea of an outcomes focused contract, but unfortunately it does so at the expense of the customers position under the contract should things not go as planned.</p>

<p>I hope to have the opportunity to discuss Flexible Contracts with Gabrielle during <a href="http://gotocon.com/aarhus-2013/">goto Aarhus 2013</a> and do one or more follow posts on Flexible Contracts.</p>

<p>Links regarding best endeavours:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ashfords.co.uk/news/reasonable_endeavours_aug10">&ldquo;All reasonable endeavours&rdquo; a lesser obligation than &ldquo;best endeavours&rdquo;</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.jonesday.com/best-efforts-and-endeavourscase-analysis-and-practical-guidance-under-us-and-uk-law-07-30-2007/">Best and EffortsCase Analysis and Practical Guidance Under U.S. and U.K. Law</a></p>

<p><a href="https://delicious.com/flatspace/endeavours">My delicious links about &ldquo;best endeavours&rdquo;</a></p>

<p>Full Disclosure:  I am receiving a free GOTO ticket from the producers in exchange for blogging about the conference.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Acceptable EULA?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/06/04/an-acceptable-eula/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-04T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/06/04/an-acceptable-eula</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is there such a thing? Until today I did not think so, but after having
watched Mixergy&rsquo;s
<a href="/web/20100907205218/http://mixergy.com/balsamiq-peldi-guilizzoni-interview/">interview</a>
with Balsamiq’s Giacomo “Peldi” Guilizzoni, I was optimistic that I
might have finally found one. Check Balsamiq’s EULA out
<a href="/web/20100907205218/http://www.balsamiq.com/images/BalsamiqEula.pdf">here</a>.
Peldi mentions in the interview that a helpful customer in-house counsel
gave him some great feedback that helped improve the license. To
whatever she told him, I would add the following:</p>

<h4>Preamble</h4>

<p>Don’t use “represents and warrants” use only “represents”. The form is
needless legalese and part of the reason why people hate lawyers. If you
don’t agree read
<a href="/web/20100907205218/http://www.adamsdrafting.com/2009/09/18/rs-and-ws-once-more-with-feeling/">this</a>
– then go change it.</p>

<h4>Definitions</h4>

<p>“Authorized Users” and “Authorized User” – makes no sense that the
plural form would have a completely different meaning than the singular.
“Authorized Users” is never used in the EULA. This might make sense when
read together with the Quote/Receipt/Invoice but I doubt it. The
definitions of “Authorized Machine” and “Authorized Server Node” do not
appear to deal well with virtual environments.</p>

<h4>Section 3 Grant of License</h4>

<p>The license granted is “irrevocable” but at he same time terminable by
Balsamiq as per section 12. This appears inconsistent. “(except pursuant
to Clause 12 below)” should be added after “irrevocable”.</p>

<h4>Section 4 No Warranty</h4>

<p>Excluding all warranties does not strike me as compatible Balsamiqs
mission to produce high quality software. You can’t claim to aim for
excellence in everything you do, and the refuse to back it up – that’s
simply not credible. On the other hand warranties provided for goods are
not appropriate for software, as these are calibrated for defects that
occur in individual instances (copies) of the product. I would suggest a
warranty that better correspond to the apparently fanatical customer
service Balsamiq provides. This does no mean warranting to fix bugs
within a certain timeframe, but it does mean warranting a meaningful
response to reported bugs etc. If you are doing it already it such a
warranty is essential free, if you make sure that the customers remedies
if you fail are manageable. If such remedies for instance only apply to
the (first) reporter of the bug, you contain the effect of the warranty
from spreading to all customers.</p>

<h4>Section 6.1 Software Maintenance – For Plug-in Versions</h4>

<p>Excellent to see inclusion of a reasonable price-escalation clause for
Software Maintenance. This is something that I have had to negotiate
many times and which any prudent licensee should always remember. You
don’t want to be
<a href="/web/20100907205218/http://www.zdnet.com/blog/howlett/sap-pulls-the-trigger-on-higher-support-costs/442">treated</a>
like SAP’s customers, do you?</p>

<h4>Section 9 Investigation of Unauthorized Use and Distribution</h4>

<p>This is a very pragmatic alternative to audit rights which especially a
company the size of Balsamiq would have very little use for. The
fairness of allocating the cost of producing the certificate to the
licensee should be considered, since this might exceed the license fee
by a factor of many in some cases. I would consider some kind of
compensation (free maintenance?) to the customer if a request for a
certificate is made and this is provided, as this is would indicate that
Balsamiqs suspicion was not well-founded.</p>

<h4>Section 10 (a) Licensee’s Restrictions</h4>

<p>Very common provision which is also very unenforceable in the EU if the
motif for the reverse engineering is a desire to “achieve the
interoperability of an independently created computer program with other
programs” (thanks to art. 5 and 6 of this
EU <a href="/web/20100907205218/http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:31991L0250:EN:HTML">directive</a>).</p>

<h4>Section 10 (b) Licensee’s Restrictions</h4>

<p>Appears superfluous. How would the customer ever unilaterally be able to
vary the “Authorized Use”? That said there might be a technicality in
California law that makes it prudent to include this.</p>

<h4>Section 10 (d) and (e) Licensee’s Restrictions</h4>

<p>WTF! I can’t refer to Balsamiq’s name or do anything that has a
“material and adverse effect on Balsamiq’s” interests. I am glad that I
did not license Balsamiq’s software before writing this post. How can
you promote Balsamiq as an open organisation in continuous dialog with
its customers, and then muffle the same audience with your EULA?</p>

<h4>Section 12 – Termination</h4>

<p>The destruction of all copies of the software is a practical
impossibility in many enterprise environments due to the back-up
strategies employed. Since this will only become a requirement in case
of a breach it might be justified nonetheless, but a more balanced
alternative might be to require the destruction of all “readily usable
copies” of the software or similar.</p>

<h4>Section 13 – Infringement Indemnification</h4>

<p>For the software in question and taking into account the size of the
vendor (Balsamiq) this is a very reasonable clause, and it is a wise
move to include indemnification if you want to have any hope selling
your software to enterprise customers.</p>

<h4>Section 14 – Limitation of Liability</h4>

<p>Good to see that the indemnification obligations are exempted from the
limitation of liability.</p>

<h4>Section 16 – Open Source Code</h4>

<p>For Balsamiq’s present product I wouldn’t worry much about the “viral”
nature of the GPL and other similar licenses, which is clearly what this
section is meant to address, but the section clearly does no harm
either. If the software was meant for combination with the customer’s
code or other software and subsequent distribution, I would be more
interested in the list of of open source products/licenses in Exhibit A
as this would enable me to assess any challenges related hereto.</p>

<h4>Section 17 – Publicity Rights</h4>

<p>This section solves a very common problem in a fairly practical way (the
customer can opt out of Balsamiqs right to use the customer for
publicity purpose prior to or any time after purchase) but a better more
honest and straight forward solution, would be to permit the customer to
opt out via the web form used to purchase the product.</p>

<h4>Section 24 – Notices</h4>

<p>While not critical why appear unreasonable by biasing this section in
Balsamiqs favour? On Export Control (especially US) you really want to
provide the relevant export control classification codes if you expect
any one to comply with the rules. In general you want to try to avoid
having your software subject to US export control rules as these are
absolutely not trivial.</p>

<p>On balance Balsamiq’s EULA is above average but still suffers from a few
weakness as outlined above. Most of these can be fixed without exposing
Balsamiq to any liability that is unmanageable.</p>

<p>DISCLAIMER: Above is not legal advice bla, bla, bla.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
