<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: software | The Limiting Factor]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/categories/software/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-21T17:54:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Martin Clausen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SAS vs World Programming - SAS' Vesion]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/07/29/sas-vs-world-programming-sas-version/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-29T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/07/29/sas-vs-world-programming-sas-version</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>SAS issued a <a href="http://www.sas.com/news/preleases/WPL.html">press release</a> today with its take on the <a href="http://www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/Ch/2010/1829.html">recent decision</a> in the case between the two companies.</p>

<p>While WPL’s <a href="http://teamwpc.co.uk/press/world_programming_secures_high_court_victory_against_SAS">press release</a> might have been s optimistic in its evaluation of the decision, SAS’ press release is a master piece of hypocrisy and highly tendentious. The headline:</p>

<blockquote><p>“Court finds World Programming Ltd. Infringed on SAS Copyrights; refers case to European Court of Justice”</p></blockquote>

<p>Technically this is wrong. The judge referred a number of key questions to the ECJ – not the case it self. More specifically the judge asked for a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Court_of_Justice#References_for_a_preliminary_ruling">preliminary ruling</a> on 6 questions (<a href="http://www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/Ch/2010/1829.html#para332">para 332</a> i, ii, iii, v, vi and viii):</p>

<blockquote><p>“i) Although I am not persuaded that Pumfrey J was wrong to conclude in <em>Navitaire</em> that, on the true interpretation of Article 1(2) of the Software Directive, copyright in computer programs does not protect programming languages from being copied, I agree with him that this is a question on which guidance from the ECJ is required (see paragraphs 211-218 above).</p>

<p>ii) Although I am not persuaded that Pumfrey J was wrong to conclude in <em>Navitaire</em> that, on the true interpretation of Article 1(2) of the Software Directive, copyright in computer programs does not protect interfaces from being copied where this can be achieved without decompiling the object code, I consider this is also a question on which guidance from the ECJ is required (see paragraphs 219-227 above).</p>

<p>iii) Although I am not persuaded that Pumfrey J was wrong to conclude in <em>Navitaire</em> that, on the true interpretation of Article 1(2) of the Software Directive, copyright in computer programs does not protect the functions of the programs from being copied, and although his decision on that point was upheld by the Court of Appeal in <em>Nova</em>, I consider that this is also a question on which guidance from the ECJ is required (see paragraphs 228-238 above).</p>

<p>…</p>

<p>v) I consider that the reasoning which supports Pumfrey J’s interpretation of Article 1(2) of the Software Directive also applies to Article 2(a) of the Information Society Directive, but again this is a question on which guidance from the ECJ is required (see paragraphs 251-256 above).</p>

<p>vi) On the assumption that Article 2(a) of the Information Society Directive is to be interpreted in the same manner as Article 1(2) of the Software Directive, WPL has not infringed SAS Institute’s copyright in the SAS Manuals by producing or testing WPS (see paragraphs 257-267 above).”</p></blockquote>

<p>SAS completely neglects to mention that the judge is clearly prepared to find in favor of WPL in all these questions and cites English precedents in support of such a decision. He asks for the ECJs confirmation of his interpretation because the basis for the rules in English law is EU Directives (see here for the<a href="http://www.hmcourts-service.gov.uk/cms/801.htm"> practice directions </a>the court operates under).</p>

<p>SAS goes on to state the following:</p>

<blockquote><p>“The court also found that WPL acted outside the scope of its license agreement for SAS Learning Edition software by using that product to develop WPL’s World Programming System (WPS) software.”</p></blockquote>

<p>What the judge actually said was this (my emphasis):</p>

<blockquote><p>vii) WPL’s use of the SAS Learning Edition falls outside the scope of the terms of the relevant licences (see paragraphs 276-290 above).</p>

<p>viii) The interpretation of Article 5(3) of the Software Directive is another question on which guidance from the ECJ is required (see paragraphs 291-311 and 314 above).</p>

<p> <em>ix) On the interpretation of Article 5(3) which I favour, WPL’s use of the Learning Edition is within Article 5(3), and to the extent that the licence terms prevent this they are null and void, with the result that none of WPL’s acts complained of was a breach of contract or an infringement of copyright except perhaps one (see paragraphs 313-315 above).</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Also on this issue SAS chooses not to disclose that the judge is prepared to find in favor of WPL.</p>

<p>Accusing WPL of spinning the courts decision and then applying tornado class spin to the decision yourself is just pathetic.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SAS vs. World Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/07/23/sas-vs-world-programming/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-23T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/07/23/sas-vs-world-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>UPDATE: I did a follow-up post on the SAS Press Release <a href="http://www.spyfoos.com/index.php/2010/07/29/sas-vs-world-programming-sas-version/">here</a></p>

<p>So the <a href="http://www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/Ch/2010/1829.html">decision</a> in “SAS Institute Inc v World Programming Ltd” has been published and it is in favor of WPL on all counts, except that the judge finds that WPL – against it’s own policy – copied certain language from SAS’ manuals into its own manuals.</p>

<p>Key questions pertaining to almost all the other claims will be submitted to the ECJ for confirmation of the judges interpretation of the law(specifically Articles 1(2) and 5(3) of the <a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:31991L0250:EN:HTML">Software Directive</a> and Article 2(a) of the <a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32001L0029:EN:HTML">Information Society Directive</a>) (see below).</p>

<p>If everything holds up this is potentially a huge win for competition in the software industry.The decision means that can re-implement the functionality of other software and reference that software and its documentation in the process, as long as you do not copy any source code or documentation. The judge (who appears to be quite technically savvy) analyses in detail how the SAS language is constructed. SAS appears to argue that the PROCS steps in the SAS Language is not a programming language, but in fact a computer program in itself. The SAS expert Dr. Ivey states the following on the matter:</p>

<p>&gt; the SAS Language was a domain specific computer language with many of the attributes of a command language, rather than a programming language</p>

<p>It is not clear to me exactly what SAS was hoping to achieve with this line of reasoning (<a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=1545404">perhaps they were trying to escape a suspected non-copyrightability of programming languages</a>) but whatever it was it did not work as the judge slightly sarcastically <a href="http://www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/Ch/2010/1829.html#para56">finds</a> that:</p>

<p>&gt; In my judgment the SAS Language is a programming language. I am comforted by the fact that this assessment coincides not only with SAS Institute’s own assessment in paragraph 6 of its Particulars of Claim and in its literature, but also with that of the anonymous author of the entry for “SAS language” in Wikipedia (as last modified on 25 April 2010), which states:
&gt;
&gt; “… SAS can be considered a general programming language, though it serves largely as a database programming language and a language with a wide variety of specialized analytic and graphic procedures.”</p>

<p>The judge also analyses whether the <em>functionality </em>of a computer program (not the source code) is itself protectable by copyright and <a href="http://www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/Ch/2010/1829.html#para236">finds</a> that:</p>

<p>&gt; Accordingly, I consider that the functionality of a computer program falls on the wrong side of the line drawn by Article 1(2) of the Software Directive, Article 9(2) of TRIPS and Article 2 of the WIPO Copyright Treaty.</p>

<p>So the functionality of a computer program is not protectable, which is not too surprising, but as the question in the judges opinion is not _<a href="http://www.translegal.com/legal-english-dictionary/acte-clair">acte clair_</a> it is submitted together with 5 other questions (<a href="http:/www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/Ch/2010/1829.html#para332">para 332</a> i, ii, iii, v, vi and viii)) to the ECJ for guidance. Among these is also the question of whether a programming language as such is protectable by copyright. The judge finds that this is probably not the case, but appears less certain on this question than the others.</p>

<p>It will be really interesting to see if this will result alternative vendors deciding to challenge other dominant software products, by producing compatible solutions that release the customers from lock-in and introduce effective competition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Source and Export Control]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/06/09/export-control-and-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-09T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/06/09/export-control-and-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ref my comments on export control rules in my previous post, it looks like these are now impacting open source in a major way. Apparently SourceForge in an effort to comply with US export control rules (specifically countries covered by sanctions administrated by <a href="http://www.ustreas.gov/offices/enforcement/ofac/">OFAC</a>) have blocked all users from Cuba, Iran, North Korea, Sudan, and Syria. <a href="http://notepad-plus-plus.org/">NotePad++</a> appears to be the first project to withdraw from SourceForge in protest.</p>

<p>UPDATE: Apparently SourceForge has now made the blocking of users from sanctioned countries <a href="http://sourceforge.net/blog/some-good-news-SourceForge-removes-blanket-blocking/">optional</a>. This leaves the assessment of whether or not a project is subject to the rules up to the project owner. As export control is quite an esoteric topic some links to guidance on the applicability of US export control rules would probably have been a good idea, but SourceForge’s consel has probably counseled against that for liability reasons.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
