<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: dave_thomas | The Limiting Factor]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/categories/dave-thomas/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-06T12:45:18+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Martin Clausen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More On GUIs and DSLs]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2015/10/06/More-On-GUIs-And-DSLs/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2015/10/06/More-On-GUIs-And-DSLs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Prior to his <a href="http://gotocon.com/cph-2015/">gotocon CPH</a> talk <a href="http://gotocon.com/cph-2015/presentation/Fast%20Data%20%E2%80%93Tools%20and%20Peopleware">&ldquo;Fast Data –Tools and Peopleware&rdquo;</a> I had a brief chat with Dave.</p>

<p>I was interested in hearing what had informed the design of his <a href="http://www.bedarra.com/product_overview.html">Ivy</a> system, especially the combination of a rich HTML based GUI and a DSL edited in the browser.</p>

<p>This post is a overview of what I consider the key take aways from the chat and some of my subsequent reflections.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Combining well known metaphors like a spreadsheet and boosting learnability example based queries with a DSL has been a very useful approach.</p></li>
<li><p>Supporting power users is a challenge but doable in a mordern web app.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>1) Firstly the app has to be designed to support that user type expects, like short cuts etc. Ivy is not just a editable field for code, but a complete IDE including debugger etc.</p>

<p>2) Secondly if you include a DSL don&rsquo;t do it to boost your ego but because it provides actual leverage. Also don&rsquo;t forget that putting a DSL out there which power users are going to trly on require that you can support it. This means that you have the physical resoources available for the long run.</p>

<ul>
<li>Building a web app offers the possibility of offloading computationally demanding operations to the backend, for instance generation of SVG graphs.</li>
</ul>


<p>Full Disclosure:  I am receiving a free GOTO ticket from the producers in exchange for blogging about the conference.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GUI DSLs]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2015/09/14/GUI-DSLs/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-14T23:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2015/09/14/GUI-DSLs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I wrote previuously I am going to the <a href="http://gotocon.com/cph-2015">goto cph conference</a> this year.</p>

<p>One speaker that I am definitively will go see is <a href="http://gotocon.com/cph-2015/presentation/The%20State%20of%20Data%203">Dave Thomas</a>. Besides being consistently entertaining Dave Thomas also has the experience required to reach into the great work of Computer Science past and show how it remains relevant the practical business challenges of today.</p>

<p>Dave&rsquo;s company has a product called <a href="http://www.bedarra.com/product_overview.html">Ivy</a>. It is a analytics product based on the programming language <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Q_(programming_language_from_Kx_Systems)">Q</a> &ndash; a decendant of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/APL_(programming_language)">APL</a>/<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K_(programming_language)">K</a> &ndash; and the <a href="http://kx.com/software.php">KDb+</a> database.</p>

<p>Ivy&rsquo;s primary usecase appears to be financial analytics, an area I know little about, but I find its approach to user interface fascinating. It shows how you can precent a contemporary web based GUI using familiar metaphors and maintain the ability to drop down to code when you need to.</p>

<p>Ivy has a very cool modern looking in-browser inteface with spreadsheet like overview of the massive volumes of data the system is designed to handle, a visual query builder and supports a wide range of visualizations. But it also has strong support for the Q language, including a debugger.</p>

<p>I hope to be able to chat with Dave about his thoughts on DSLs and GUIs during the conference and get his take on questions like &ldquo;When do you want both?&rdquo;, &ldquo;What kind of IDE do you need if you want to support non-programmers programming?&rdquo;, &ldquo;Are projectional editors the future of DSLs?&rdquo; etc. and report here on the conversation.</p>

<p>Full Disclosure:  I am receiving a free GOTO ticket from the producers in exchange for blogging about the conference.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
