<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: java | The Limiting Factor]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/categories/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-05T14:17:54+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Martin Clausen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hit Record!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2013/09/30/hit-record/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T16:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2013/09/30/hit-record</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Richard Baeckman just did an excellent presentation on <a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javaseproducts/mission-control/java-mission-control-1998576.html">Java Flight Recorder</a> at <a href="http://gotocon.com/aarhus-2013/">goto Aarhus 2013</a>. Java Flight Recorder is an &ndash; enhanced &ndash; port of JRockit Flight Recorder to the Oracle(Sun) JVM. It ships with  Java SE Development Kit 7u40 and includes a very nifty GUI called Java Mission Control that provides an excellent overvie of all the data collected in your recordings. I was very interested in seeing how useful JFR is when running Clojure code. Fortunately installation is very easy. After installing <a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html">Java Platform (JDK) 7u40</a> I just added the following options to my project.clj file.</p>

<p><code>:jvm-opts ["-XX:+UnlockCommercialFeatures" "-XX:+FlightRecorder"]</code></p>

<p>On OS X you have to start the JMC from a terminal invoking the binary located at:</p>

<p><code>/Library/Java/JavaVirtualMachines/jdk1.7.0_40.jdk/Contents/Home/bin/jmc</code></p>

<p>This brings up the JMC GUI. If you start your Clojure app (in my case Rich&rsquo;s ants.clj), your jvm(s) should be visible under the JVM Browser tab. From here you can start a recording by double-clicking the relevant JVM, right-clicking the Flight Recorder entry and choosing &ldquo;Start Flight Recording&hellip;&rdquo;. I have inlcuded a screenshot below of a 1 minute recording of ants.clj. As you can tell JFR collects an immense amount of information but the overhead is minimal, approx 3% according to Richard.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/jmc.png" title="Java Mission Control Screenshot" alt="Java Mission Control" /></p>

<p>Please do note that the Java Flight Recorder and JMC are both Commercial Features, which I have written about previously <a href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2011/07/28/oracle-java-7-and-commercial-features/">here</a>. This means that neither JFR and JMC may be used for production purposes without a separate payable license from Oracle. There is currently no public information regarding prices and other conditions available from Oracle.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle vs Google - Implementing the JVM Specification]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/08/24/oracle-vs-google-implementing-the-jvm-specification/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-24T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spyfoos.com/blog/2010/08/24/oracle-vs-google-implementing-the-jvm-specification</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A lot has already been written on the Oracle vs. Google Android <a href="http:/www.scribd.com/doc/35811761/Oracle-s-complaint-against-Google-for-Java-patent-infringement">case</a>. <a href="http://blog.headius.com/2010/08/my-thoughts-on-oracle-v-google.html">Some</a> of it is brilliant. <a href="http://tirania.org/blog/archive/2010/Aug-13.html">Some</a> is illuminating, <a href="http://fosspatents.blogspot.com/2010/08/oracle-vs-google-licensing-issues.html">some</a> less so. Since the complaint is devoid of any details as to how Android infringes upon the patents listed in the complaint, I will focus on the alleged copyright infringement. Here too Oracle is not specific but it is clear that the infringement is alleged at least in part on the basis of unlicensed use of specification(s) in which Oracle holds copyright(cf. Count VIII section 38 of the complaint) .</p>

<p>For context Oracle in the complaint defines Android as:</p>

<p>The Android operating-system software “stack” consists of Java applications running on a Java-based object-oriented application framework, and core libraries running on a “Dalvik” virtual machine (VM) that features just-in-time (JIT) compilation.</p>

<p>One aspect that appears to confuse matters is what <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dalvik_(software)">Dalvik</a> is. Dalvik is VM but <em>not</em> a Java VM. Dalvik executes .dex files which are created from .class files produced by a Java compiler. The .dex files are created by a tool called “dx”. As such Dalvik does not implement the Java Language Specification. The “dx” tool does however appear to implement part of the Java <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/jvms/second_edition/html/VMSpecTOC.doc.html">Virtual Machine Specification</a>, namely <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/jvms/second_edition/html/ClassFile.doc.html">the part</a> that specifies the .class file format. As the “dx” tool does not comply with the conditions of SUN’s <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/jvms/second_edition/html/Copyright.doc.html">license grant</a> the question is then: Does Google need a copyright license from SUN to implement the “dx” tool?</p>

<p>From a European perspective the recent SAS vs. World Programming(WPL) case sheds some very interesting light on this issue. The case a addresses the application of copyright to programming languages, interfaces and functionality. While the judge submits all of the questions to the ECJ for a preliminary ruling, he clearly thinks, on the strength English precedents(specifically the Navitaire <a href="http://www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/Ch/2004/1725.html">case</a>) that neither programming languages, interfaces or functionality is protectable by copyright. If the ECJ concurs with the judges&nbsp;opinion it is hard to see why Google would need a license to implement the .class file format as part of their “dx” tool.</p>

<p>Would the analysis under US copyright law be the same?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
